מבוא 00:00:01,989 --&gt;
This is a video for anyone who already knows
00:00:06,060 3
what eigenvalues and eigenvectors are, and
who might enjoy a quick way to compute them
הטריק, אבל אם
in the case of 2x2 matrices. If you’re unfamiliar
with eigenvalues, take a look at this video
אפשר הייתי
which introduces them.
רוצה שתגלה אותו
You can skip ahead if you just want to see
מחדש בעצמך,
אז בשביל זה
let’s lay down a little background.
00:00:23,349 --&gt;
As a quick reminder, if the effect of a linear
transformation on a given vector is to scale
00:00:28,550 8 לעתים
it by some constant, we call it an "eigenvector"
of the transformation, and we call the relevant
קרובות מסומן
scaling factor the corresponding "eigenvalue,"
באות למבדה. כשאתה
כותב את זה
a little bit, what you see is that if the
כמשוואה ומסדר מחדש 00:00:47,320
number lambda is an eigenvalue of a matrix
A, then the matrix (A minus lambda times the
--&gt; 00:00:53,190 12
identity) must send some nonzero vector, namely
the corresponding eigenvector, to the zero
מהמטריצה המשתנה הזו
vector, which in turn means the determinant
חייבים להיות 0.
אוקיי, זה הכל
to say, but again, I’m assuming all of this
קצת מלא
is review for anyone watching.
פה 00:01:09,960 --&gt;
So, the usual way to compute eigenvalues,
how I used to do it, and how I believe most
00:01:12,829 00:01:12,829
students are taught to carry it out, is to
subtract the unknown value lambda off the
--&gt; 00:01:17,939 17
diagonals and then solve for when the determinant
שווה ל-0.
פעולה זו כרוכה
expand out and simplify to get a clean quadratic
תמיד בכמה שלבים
polynomial, what's known as the “characteristic
polynomial” of the matrix. The eigenvalues
ל-00:01:32,630 --&gt; 00:01:38,069
are the roots of this polynomial. So to find
them you have to apply the quadratic formula,
21 שלבים נוספים
which itself typically requires one or two
של פישוט.
בכנות, התהליך לא נורא. אבל
at least for 2x2 matrices, there’s a much
00:01:52,710 --&gt;
more direct way to get at this answer. And
if you want to rediscover this trick, there
00:01:57,049 25 הסכום
are only three relevant facts you need to
know, each of which is worth knowing in its
של שני
own right and can help you with other problem-solving.
הערכים האלכסוניים האלה
Number 1: The trace of a matrix, which is
שווה לסכום הערכים
העצמיים. או
way to phrase it, more useful for our purposes,
אחר 00:02:14,700 --&gt;
is that the mean of the two eigenvalues is
the same as the mean of these two diagonal
00:02:18,959 30
entries.
31 הגיוני אם
Number 2: The determinant of a matrix, our
usual ad-bc formula, is equal to the product
אתה מבין שערכים
of the two eigenvalues. And this should kind
עצמיים מתארים
כמה אופרטור מותח
in a particular direction and that the determinant
את החלל 00:02:37,720
describes how much an operator scales areas
(or volumes) as a whole.
--&gt; 00:02:42,189
Now before getting to the third fact, notice
how you can essentially read these first two
35 הרבה למטה.
values out of the matrix without really writing
קח את המטריצה הזו כאן כדוגמה.
מיד אתה יכול
the eigenvalues is the same as the mean of
לדעת שהממוצע
8 and 6, which is 7. Likewise, most linear
algebra students are pretty well-practiced
של 00:02:55,970 --&gt;
at finding the determinant, which in this
case works out to be 48 - 8 So right away
00:03:02,420 39
you know that the product of our two eigenvalues
הוא 40.
עכשיו קח רגע כדי
what will be our third relevant fact, which
לראות איך אתה יכול
is how to recover two numbers when you know
their mean and you know their product.
לגזור 00:03:17,079 --&gt; 00:03:21,860
Here, let's focus on this example. You know
the two values are evenly spaced around 7,
43 בואו נקרא לזה
so they look like 7 plus or minus something;
משהו &quot;ד&quot; למרחק.
אתה גם יודע שהמכפלה
numbers is 40. Now to find d, notice that
של שני הדוגמאות
this product expands really nicely, it works
out as a difference of squares. So from there,
האלה 00:03:40,239 --&gt;
you can directly find d: d^2 is 7^2 - 40,
or 9, which means d itself is 3.
00:03:45,480 47 מסתבר
In other words, the two values for this very
להיות 4 ו-10.
אבל המטרה שלנו היא
want to think this through each time, so let’s
טריק מהיר, ואתה לא
wrap up what we just did in a general formula.
For any mean, m and product, p, the distance
00:04:06,239 --&gt; 00:04:12,610 51
squared is always going to be m^2 - p. This
gives the third key fact, which is that when
אתה יכול לכתוב את
two numbers have a mean m and a product p,
שני המספרים האלה כ-m
± sqrt(m^2 -
p) זה מהיר למדי
if you ever forget it, and it’s essentially
לגזירה on the fly
just a rephrasing of the difference of squares
formula. But even still it’s a fact worth
00:04:34,490 --&gt; 00:04:39,360 56
memorizing so that you have it at the tip
of your fingers.
כתב לנו ג&#39;ינגל מהיר
In fact, my friend Tim from the channel acapellascience
כדי להפוך אותו לקצת
יותר בלתי נשכח.
m פלוס מינוס squaaaare
minus p (ping!)
שורש שלי בריבוע
Let me show you how this works, say for the
matrix [[3,1], [4,1]]. You start by bringing
00:04:53,880 --&gt; 00:04:59,069
to mind the formula, maybe stating it all
in your head. But when you write it down,
61 p תוך כדי.
you fill in the appropriate values of m and
אז בדוגמה זו,
הממוצע של הערכים העצמיים
of 3 and 1, which is 2. So the thing you start
זהה לממוצע 00:05:19,030
writing is 2 ± sqrt(2^2 - …). Then the
product of the eigenvalues is the determinant,
--&gt; 00:05:26,780 65 עשוי
which in this example is 3*1 - 1*4, or -1.
So that’s the final thing you fill in. This
לזהות שזו אותה
means the eigenvalues are 2±sqrt(5). You
מטריצה שבה השתמשתי בהתחלה,
אך שימו לב
much more directly we can get at the answer.
כיצד 00: 05:47,370 --&gt;
Here, try another one. This time the mean
of the eigenvalues is the same as the mean
00:05:52,190 69 הוא
of 2 and 8, which is 5. So again, you start
writing out the formula but this time writing
2*8 - 7*1, או
5 in place of m [song]. And then the determinant
9. אז בדוגמה
זו, הערכים העצמיים נראים
simplifies even further as 9 and 1.
כמו 5 ±
You see what I mean about how you can basically
just start writing down the eigenvalues while
sqrt(16), אשר 00:06:19,590
staring at the matrix? It’s typically just
the tiniest bit of simplifying at the end.
--&gt; 00:06:23,800 73
Honestly, I’ve found myself using this trick
הרבה כאשר אני
משרטט הערות מהירות הקשורות
as examples. I’ve been working on a video
לאלגברה לינארית ורוצה
about matrix exponents, where eigenvalues
pop up a lot, and I realized it’s just very
להשתמש במטריצות קטנות
handy if students can read off the eigenvalues
from small examples without losing the main
00:06:37,039 --&gt; 00:06:41,800
line of thought by getting bogged down in
77 חישוב אחר.
כדוגמה מהנה נוספת, תסתכל
set of three different matrices, which come
על המכניקה של
up a lot in quantum mechanics, they're known
as the Pauli spin matrices. If you know quantum
00:06:54,190 --&gt; 00:06:59,419
mechanics, you’ll know that the eigenvalues
of matrices are highly relevant to the physics
81, תן לזה רק
they describe, and if you don’t know quantum
להיות הצצה קטנה
לאופן שבו החישובים
to real applications.
האלה באמת רלוונטיים
The mean of the diagonal in all three cases
is 0, so the mean of the eigenvalues in all
00:07:12,639 --&gt; 00: 07:19,990
cases is 0, which makes our formula look especially
simple.
85 הקובעים של
What about the products of the eigenvalues,
המטריצות הללו? עבור הראשון,
זה 0 - 1 או -1. השני
also looks like 0 - 1, but it takes a moment
00:07:36,430 --&gt; 00:07:42,310
more to see because of the complex numbers.
And the final one looks like -1 - 0. So in
89 יודע שהם
all cases, the eigenvalues simplify to be
±1. Although in this case, you really don’t
מרווחים באופן שווה
need the formula to find two values if you
סביב 0 והמוצר
שלהם הוא -1.
אם אתה סקרן, בהקשר
mechanics, these matrices describe observations
של קוואנטום 00:07:59,759
you might make about a particle's spin in
the x, y or z directions. The fact that their
--&gt; 00:08:04,470 94
eigenvalues are ±1 corresponds with the idea
that the values for the spin that you would
או לגמרי באחר,
observe would be either entirely in one direction
בניגוד למשהו שנע
בין לבין. אולי
wonder how exactly this works, or why you
היית רוצה 00:08:20,680
would use 2x2 matrices that have complex numbers
to describe spin in three dimensions. And
--&gt; 00:08:26,259 98 כי
those would be fair questions, just outside
the scope of what I want to talk about here.
רציתי מקרה שבו
You know it’s funny, I wrote this section
יש לך מטריצות
2x2 שאינן רק
or homework problems, ones where they actually
דוגמאות צעצועים 00:08:38,970
come up in practice, and quantum mechanics
is great for that. But the thing is after
--&gt; 00:08:43,880 102
I made it I realized that the whole example
kind of undercuts the point I’m trying to
להשתמש ב- השיטה
make. For these specific matrices, when you
המסורתית, זו עם
פולינומים אופייניים, היא בעצם
it might actually faster. I mean, take a look
מהירה באותה מידה;
a the first one: The relevant determinant
directly gives you a characteristic polynomial
00:08:58,700 --&gt; 00:09:03,390
of lambda^2 - 1, and clearly, that has roots
of plus and minus 1. Same answer when you
106 עבור המטריצה
do the second matrix, lambda^2 - 1. And as
האחרונה, שכח לעשות
חישובים, מסורתיים או
already a diagonal matrix, so those diagonal
אחרים, זה 00:09:20,940
entries are the eigenvalues!
--&gt; 00:09:23,510 00:09:23,510
However, the example is not totally lost to
our cause. Where you will actually feel the
-- &gt; 00:09:28,850
speed up is in the more general case where
you take a linear combination of these three
111 אחד, פלוס b
matrices and then try to compute the eigenvalues.
כפול השני, פלוס
You might write this as a times the first
c כפול השלישי.
במכניקת הקוונטים, זה
describe spin observations in a general direction
00:09:47,360 --&gt; 00:09:53,240
of a vector with coordinates [a, b, c]. More
specifically, you should assume this vector
116 עדיין
is normalized, meaning a^2 + b^2 + c^2 = 1.
When you look at this new matrix, it’s immediate
יהיה אפס, וייתכן
to see that the mean of the eigenvalues is
שתהנה גם להשהות
לרגע קצר כדי
of those eigenvalues is still -1, and then
לאשר שהמוצר 00:10:13,560
from there concluding what the eigenvalues
must be. And this time, the characteristic
--&gt; 00:10: 18,710
polynomial approach would be by comparison
a lot more cumbersome, definitely harder to
120 אינו
do in your head.
שונה מהותית ממציאת
To be clear, using the mean-product formula
שורשים של הפולינום
האופייני; I 00:10:33,110
mean, it can't be, they're solving the same
--&gt; 00:10:37,160 125
problem. One way to think about this, actually,
is that the mean-product formula is a nice
שורשי הריבוע
way to solve quadratic in general (and some
viewers of the channel may recognize this).
בהינתן המקדמים שלו,
This about it: When you’re trying to find
זה מצב אחר
שבו אתה מכיר
sum of two values, and you also know their
את המקדם 00:10:50,950
product, but you’re trying to recover the
original two values.
--&gt; 00:10:54,820 129,
Specifically, if the polynomial is normalized
so that this leading coefficient is 1, then
שהוא -פי
the mean of the roots will be -½ times this
1 מסכום השורשים
הללו. לדוגמא על
screen that makes the mean 5. And the product
00:11:12,820 --&gt; 00:11:17,610
of the roots is even easier, it’s just the
constant term no adjustments needed. So from
133 גרסה
there, you would apply the mean product formula
and that gives you the roots.
קלה יותר של
On the one hand, you could think of this as
הנוסחה הריבועית
המסורתית. אבל היתרון
is that it's fewer symbols to memorize, it's
האמיתי 00:11:34,200 --&gt; 00:11:37,370
that each one of them carries more meaning
with it.
137 אתה לא
The whole point of this eigenvalue trick is
that because you can read out the mean and
צריך לעבור את
product directly from looking at the matrix,
שלב הביניים של
הגדרת הפולינום האופייני.
You can jump straight to writing down the
00:11:49,930 --&gt; 00:11:54,339
roots without ever explicitly thinking about
what the polynomial looks like. But to do
141 לקהל מאוד
that we need a version of the quadratic formula
where the terms carry some kind of meaning.
ספציפי, אבל זה
I realize that this is a very specific trick,
משהו שהלוואי שידעתי
בקולג&#39;, אז אם
to know any students who might benefit from
יקרה לך
this, consider sharing it with them.
00:12:08,240 --&gt; 00:12:10,330
The hope is that it’s not just one more
thing to memorize, but that the framing reinforces
00:12 :10,330 --&gt;
some other nice facts worth knowing, like
how the trace and determinant relate to eigenvalues.
00:12:15,140 146 קחו
If you want to prove those facts, by the way,
רגע להרחיב את
הפולינום האופייני
hard about the meaning of each of these coefficients.
למטריצה כללית, וחשבו
Many thanks to Tim, for ensuring that this
mean-product formula will stay stuck in all
ש-00:12:32,449 --&gt; 00:12:36,420
of our heads for at least a few months. If
you don’t know about acapellascience, please
150 בפרט, הוא
do check it out. "The Molecular Shape of You",
אחד הדברים הגדולים
ביותר באינטרנט.